{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Short distance transportation of grain, gravel, sand, ash, asphalt etc. is done by using a __________ conveyor.", "opta": "flight", "optb": "slat or drag", "optc": "ribbon", "optd": "screw", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Equivalent diameter of a particle is the diameter of the sphere having the same", "opta": "ratio of surface to volume as the actual volume.", "optb": "ratio of volume to surface as the particle.", "optc": "volume as the particle.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If dp is the equivalent diameter of a non-spherical particle, Vp its volume and sp its surface area, then its sphericity is \u03a6s is defined by", "opta": "\u03a6s = 6 Vp/dp sp", "optb": "\u03a6s = Vp/dp sp", "optc": "\u03a6s = 6 dp Sp/Vp", "optd": "\u03a6s = dp Sp/Vp", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power required to drive a ball mill with a particular ball load is proportional to (where, D = diameter of ball mill )", "opta": "D", "optb": "1/D", "optc": "D2.5", "optd": "1/D2.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Recycled coarse material to the grinder by a classifier is termed as circulating load.", "optb": "Wear and tear in wet crushing is more than that in dry crushing of materials.", "optc": "Size enlargement (opposite of size reduction) is not a mechanical operation.", "optd": "A 'dust catcher' is simply an enlargement in a pipeline which permits the solids to settle down due to reduction in velocity of the dust laden gas.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In continuous filtration (at a constant pressure drop), filtrate flow rate varies inversely as the", "opta": "square root of the velocity.", "optb": "square of the viscosity.", "optc": "filtration time only.", "optd": "washing time only.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For sizing of fine materials, the most suitable equipment is a", "opta": "trommel", "optb": "grizzly", "optc": "shaking screen", "optd": "vibrating screen", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not categorised as a \"mechanical operation\" ?", "opta": "Agitation", "optb": "Filtration", "optc": "Size enlargement", "optd": "Humidification", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a pressure filter ?", "opta": "Leaf filter (Moore filter).", "optb": "Plate and flame filter.", "optc": "Rotary drum filter.", "optd": "Sand filter.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tabular bowl centrifuges as compared to disk bowl centrifuges", "opta": "operate at higher speed.", "optb": "employ bowl of larger diameter.", "optc": "can not be operated under pressure/vacuum.", "optd": "can't be used for separation of fine suspended solids from a liquid.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pebble mills are tumbling mills widely used for grinding in the manufacture of paints & pigments and cosmetic industries, where iron contamination in the product is highly objectionable. Pebbles used in pebble mill are made of", "opta": "bronze", "optb": "stainless steel", "optc": "flint or porcelain", "optd": "concrete", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Filter aids like asbestos, kieselguhr, diatomaceous earth etc. are used to increase the porosity of the final filter cake & reducing the cake resistance during filtration. Filter aid is", "opta": "added to the feed slurry.", "optb": "precoated on the filter medium prior to filtration.", "optc": "separated from the cake by dissolving solids or by burning it off.", "optd": "all 'a', 'b'&'c'.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relationships between co-efficinet of friction (\u03bc) between rock & roll and a (half of the angle of nip) of the particle to be crushed is correct ?", "opta": "\u03bc > tan \u03b1", "optb": "\u03bc \u2265 tan \u03b1", "optc": "\u03bc > tan 2\u03b1", "optd": "\u03bc \u2264 tan \u03b1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement pertaining to the roll crushers.", "opta": "Maximum feed size determines the required roll diameter.", "optb": "For hard material's crushing, the reduction ratio should not exceed 4.", "optc": "Both the rolls run necessarily at the same speed.", "optd": "Reduction ratio and differential roll speed affect production rate & energy consumed per unit of surface produced.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an ultrafine grinder (colloid mill)?", "opta": "Micronizers", "optb": "Agitated mills and fluid energy mills", "optc": "Toothed roll crusher", "optd": "Hammer mills with internal classification", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two particles are called to be equal settling, if they are having the same.", "opta": "size.", "optb": "specific gravity.", "optc": "terminal velocities in the same fluid & in the same field of force.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for handling fibrous and dense slurries ?", "opta": "Propeller agitator", "optb": "Cone type agitator", "optc": "Turbine agitator", "optd": "Radial propeller agitator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ centrifuge is normally used in sugar mills.", "opta": "Tubular bowl", "optb": "Disc-bowl", "optc": "Suspended batch basket", "optd": "Perforated horizontal basket continuous", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Solid particles separation based on the difference in their flow velocities through fluids is termed as the", "opta": "clarification", "optb": "classification", "optc": "elutriation", "optd": "sedimentation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diatomaceous earth is a/an", "opta": "explosive", "optb": "filter aid", "optc": "filter medium", "optd": "catalyst", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The distribution given by microscopic analysis of powder is", "opta": "number", "optb": "length", "optc": "area", "optd": "volume", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Number of particles in a crushed solid sample is given by (where, m = mass of particles in a sample, Vp = volume of one particle, \u03c1= density of particles)", "opta": "m/\u03c1 . Vp", "optb": "m . \u03c1/Vp", "optc": "m . Vp/\u03c1", "optd": "Vp/m . \u03c1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a non-spherical particle, the sphericity", "opta": "is defined as the ratio of surface area of a sphere having the same volume as the particle to the actual surface area of the particle.", "optb": "has the dimension of length.", "optc": "is always less than 1.", "optd": "is the ratio of volume of a sphere having the same surface area as the particle to the actual volume of the particle.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In washing type plate and frame filter press, the ratio of washing rate to the final filtrate rate is", "opta": "4", "optb": "1/4", "optc": "1", "optd": "1/2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ball mills and tube mills with flint or porcelain balls are used for size reduction of", "opta": "asbestos", "optb": "rubber", "optc": "non-metallic ores", "optd": "limestone", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Size reduction of __________ is accomplished in steam heated rollers and roll crushers.", "opta": "resins", "optb": "gums", "optc": "hard rubber", "optd": "waxes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a belt conveyor depends upon two factors. If one is the cross-section of the load, the other is the __________ of the belt.", "opta": "speed", "optb": "thickness", "optc": "length", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a part of the Blake jaw crusher?", "opta": "Hanger", "optb": "Check plates", "optc": "Toggles", "optd": "Pitman", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a force greater than that of gravity is used to separate solids & fluids of different densities, the process is termed as the", "opta": "sedimentation", "optb": "flocculation", "optc": "dispersion", "optd": "centrifugation", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Filter aid is used to", "opta": "increase the rate of filtration.", "optb": "decrease the pressure drop.", "optc": "increase the porosity of the cake.", "optd": "act as a support base for the septum.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following mineral dressing operations is termed as 'comminution'?", "opta": "Panning", "optb": "Spiralling", "optc": "Tabling", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a pneumatic conveying system depends upon the", "opta": "bulk density of materials.", "optb": "pressure of the conveying air.", "optc": "diameter of the conveying line.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Close circuit grinding is more economical than open circuit grinding.", "optb": "Cod oil, beef tallow or aluminium stearates are used as grinding aids in cement 'industries'.", "optc": "The equipment used for the removal of traces of solids from a liquid is called a classifier.", "optd": "Size enlargement is a mechanical operation exemplified by medicinal tablet making.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Gravity settling process is not involved in the working of a", "opta": "hydrocyclone", "optb": "classifier", "optc": "dorr-thickener", "optd": "sedimentation tank", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Froth floatation is the most suitable for treating", "opta": "iron ores", "optb": "sulphide ores", "optc": "quartzite", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy required per unit mass to grind limestone particles of very large size to 100 \u03bcm is 12.7 kWh/ton. An estimate (using Bond's law) of the energy to grind the particles from a very large size to 50 \u03bcrn is", "opta": "6.35 kWh/ton", "optb": "9.0 kWh/ton", "optc": "18 kWh/ton", "optd": "25.4 kWh/ton", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the most suitable for cleaning of fine coal dust (<0.5 mm) ?", "opta": "Trough washer", "optb": "Baum jig washer", "optc": "Spiral separator", "optd": "Froth floatation", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement:", "opta": "Removal of iron from ceramic material is necessitated (by magnetic separation method) so as to avoid discolouration of ceramic products.", "optb": "The operating cost of shaking screen is more than that of a vibrating screen.", "optc": "Screen capacity does not depend upon the specific gravity of the minerals.", "optd": "Asphalt is best crushed using toothed roll crusher.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Range of compressibility co-efficient of the commercial compressible cake obtained in filtration operation is", "opta": "0.01 to 0.1", "optb": "0.1 to 0.3", "optc": "0.2 to 0.8", "optd": "0.2 to 0.4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Highly viscous liquids & pastes are agitated by", "opta": "propellers", "optb": "turbine agitators", "optc": "multiple blade paddles", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of 'angle of nip' is generally about", "opta": "16\u00b0", "optb": "32\u00b0", "optc": "52\u00b0", "optd": "64\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Size reduction of the __________ can be suitably done by ball mills, crushing rolls and rod mills.", "opta": "metalliferrous ores", "optb": "non-metallic ores", "optc": "basic slags", "optd": "asbestos & mica", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sulphuric acid mist is arrested by using a __________ scrubber.", "opta": "packed wet", "optb": "hollow wet", "optc": "venturi", "optd": "co-current", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main size reduction operation in ultrafine grinders is", "opta": "cutting", "optb": "attrition", "optc": "compression", "optd": "impact", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of a hammer crusher,", "opta": "crushing takes place by impact breaking.", "optb": "maximum acceptable feed size is 30 cms.", "optc": "reduction ratio can be varied by adjusting the distance from cage to hammers.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Jigging is a technique by which different particles can be", "opta": "separated by particle size.", "optb": "separated by particle density.", "optc": "separated by particle shape.", "optd": "mixed.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crushing of mineral particles is accomplished in a 'cage mill', when one or more alloy steel bars are revolved in opposite directions. It is a type of __________ mill.", "opta": "impact", "optb": "roll", "optc": "vibratory", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Balls for ball mills are never made of", "opta": "forged/cast steel", "optb": "lead", "optc": "cast iron", "optd": "alloy steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "200 mesh screen means 200 openings per", "opta": "cm2", "optb": "cm", "optc": "inch", "optd": "inch2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is the most commonly used 'filter aid'.", "opta": "Diatomaceous earth", "optb": "Fuller's earth", "optc": "Vermiculite", "optd": "Semi-plastic clay", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}